Guide to the University of Chicago Chess Club Records 1965-1984
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Chess Club. Records
1965-1984
1 linear foot (2 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
From 1945 through 1986, the University of Chicago Chess Club ranked among the nation’s finest intercollegiate teams, winning the national championship a record seven times. These records contain membership lists, correspondence, match summaries, and newspaper clippings relating to the team which were compiled between 1965 and 1984 by former Chess Club president, Harold Winston.
Information on Use
Access
Open for research.
No restrictions.
Historical Note
The University of Chicago Chess Club ranks as one of the most successful chess teams in intercollegiate history. The team captured the Pan-American Intercollegiate Chess Championship title a record seven times, winning in 1945, 1956, 1958, 1968, 1972, 1973, and 1986. In addition to their competition schedule, members of the Chess Club dedicated themselves to promoting chess on campus, sponsoring intramural tournaments, educational opportunities, and lectures and demonstrations by visiting Grand Masters.
Scope Note
The University of Chicago Chess Club Records contains extensive documentation of the chess club’s activities from 1965 to 1983. These materials were collected and compiled by Harold Winston, a former president of the chess club, historian of the Intercollegiate Chess Association, and Chairman/CEO of the World Chess Hall of Fame. Among the documents contained here are membership lists, official rankings of chess club members, match summaries and results, and financial records. Members of the club were also active in promoting chess on campus, and many broadsides announcing intramural tournaments and chess-related lectures are collected here. Additionally, the collection includes numerous newspaper clippings relating to the chess club’s back-to-back Pan-American Intercollegiate Chess Championships in 1972 and 1973. Also documented is significant information on the founding of the Chicago Intercollegiate Chess League, a citywide conference comprised of teams from the University of Chicago, Northwestern University, Loyola University, Roosevelt University, the University of Illinois-Chicago, Southwestern City College, and Loop City College. Included are the league’s constitution, correspondence, newsletters, and match results from 1969 to 1977.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Student Activities Office. Records
Subject Headings
Winston, Harold; University of Chicago Chess Club; Chess -- United States; Student activities
INVENTORY
- Chicago Intercollegiate Chess League, constitution, correspondence, match results, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Chicago Intercollegiate Chess League, correspondence, announcements, match results, 1970-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Chicago Intercollegiate Chess League, announcements, newsletters, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Finances, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- General records, campus events, membership lists, match results, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- General records, correspondence, match results, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- General records, constitution, broadsides, match results, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- General records, correspondence, finances, match summaries, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- General records, correspondence, broadsides, finances, team photos, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- General records, correspondence, finances, press releases, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- General records, membership, match summaries, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- General records, membership, broadsides, correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- General records, membership, broadsides, correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- General records, membership, correspondence, clippings, 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- General records, membership, match results, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Membership lists, 1933-1983, compiled by Harold Winston, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Newspaper clippings, 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Ratings of club members, 1966-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)